const e=JSON.parse('[{"question":"Aripiprazole is","options":{"A":"A partial agonist at the dopamine receptor","B":"A full agonist at the dopamine receptor","C":"A dopamine receptor antagonist","D":"An inverse agonist","E":"A reuptake inhibitor at the dopamine receptor"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"When a neurotransmitter has a stimulating effect on receptors, this leads to agonistic actions. Drugs which stimulate receptors similar to these neurotransmitters are therefore called agonists. Drugs which block the action of the neurotransmitter on the receptors are antagonists. They act only in the presence of the neurotransmitter and do not have any intrinsic activity on their own. Inverse agonists have the opposite action of an agonist. For example, instead of opening an agonist operated channel, they close the channel after binding to the receptor. Inverse agonists thus have intrinsic activity (can act even in the absence of neurotransmitter molecules in the vicinity) and so can also be blocked by the antagonist. Partial agonists act as net agonists in the absence of the neurotransmitter, but act as a net antagonist in the presence of the neurotransmitter. Aripiprazole is a partial agonist at the dopamine (D) receptor. 2 Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 532."},{"question":"Lofexidine is an","options":{"A":"Alpha 2 autoreceptor agonist","B":"Alpha 1 postsynaptic agonist","C":"Alpha 2 autoreceptor antagonist","D":"Alpha 2 heteroceptor agonist","E":"Noradrenaline reuptake inhibitor"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Lofexidine is an alpha 2 agonist which acts at the autoreceptor. When the presynaptic autoreceptors are stimulated, they generally stop the release of the particular neurotransmitter. Thus they act as a brake. Lofexidine stimulates the alpha 2 autoreceptors, thus stopping the release of noradrenaline into the synapse. The antagonists of autoreceptors increase the release of the neurotransmitter. In the case of serotonin, 5HT are autoreceptors. Some alpha 2 1B receptors are found on serotonergic neurones and control the release of 5HT; these alpha 2 receptors are called heteroreceptors. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 459."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a reuptake inhibitor?","options":{"A":"Cocaine","B":"Sertraline","C":"Clomipramine","D":"Bupropion","E":"Buspirone"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Buspirone is a partial agonist at 5-HT autoreceptors and can infl uence the fi ring of 1A serotonergic (5-HT) neurones. Neurotransmitters in the synaptic cleft are actively transported back into the presynaptic neurone by a reuptake pump. Most antidepressants block this pump, thus increasing the availability of the monoamine neurotransmitters. Cocaine is a dopamine reuptake inhibitor. Bupropion inhibits reuptake of both dopamine and noradrenaline. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, pp. 1279–1281."},{"question":"Which of the following combinations is NOT paired correctly?","options":{"A":"Alprazolam: benzodiazepines","B":"Zopiclone: hypnotics","C":"Haloperidol: butyrophenones","D":"Phenytoin: anticonvulsant","E":"Acamprosate: opiates"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Phenytoin is an anticonvulsant. Alprazolam is a benzodiazepine and it is not used as a mood stabilizer; valproate, lithium, lamotrigine, and carbamazepine can be considered as mood stabilizers. Haloperidol is a butyrophenone and not a phenothiazine. Acamprosate is used to treat alcohol dependence. It is not an opiate. It has a structure similar to GABA and it is thought to act via glutamate receptor mechanism. Zopiclone is not a benzodiazepine. It is a hypnotic classed with other ‘Z drugs’; Z drugs are non-benzodiazepines which act on the GABA complex but at a slightly different site than benzodiazepines. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1018.160 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Paralytic ileus is most likely to be associated with which one of the following antipsychotics?","options":{"A":"Olanzapine","B":"Haloperidol","C":"Clozapine","D":"Amisulpride","E":"Thioridazine148 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Clozapine causes anticholinergic effects by blocking muscarinic (M3) receptors. This can cause side-effects such as dry mouth, constipation, loss of accommodation, and urinary retention. Constipation is a side-effect in around 15% of patients taking clozapine, and, in most, simple advice about diet and fl uid intake is suffi cient. More signifi cant ileus is an uncommon but potentially more serious side-effect. It may particularly be associated with bowel surgery. It could potentially be fatal. Though isolated reports of similar problems with olanzapine and risperidone have been recorded, these are not well-established associations. Taylor D et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 54."},{"question":"Which route is most liable for fi rst-pass metabolism?","options":{"A":"Sublingual","B":"Intramuscular","C":"Subcutaneous","D":"Oral","E":"Inhalational"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Orally administered drugs reach the liver via the portal circulation. If hepatic metabolism is extensive, a large amount of drug will be removed during this fi rst passage through the liver. Thus, even if a drug is extensively absorbed, fi rst-pass removal will reduce its systemic availability. So, drugs administered parenterally may need lower dosage compared to the same compound taken orally. Apart from the liver, fi rst pass metabolism also takes place in gut mucosa, muscle tissue, and lung parenchyma, albeit to a smaller extent. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1278."},{"question":"Which of the following statements regarding treatment adherence is FALSE?","options":{"A":"Non-adherence occurs in up to 10% of people with schizophrenia.","B":"Non-adherence increases relapse rate in schizophrenia.","C":"Non-adherence is associated with poor insight.","D":"Adherence is affected by the route of administration.","E":"Adverse effect is a major factor contributing to non-adherence."},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Non-adherence occurs in up to 40–60% of patients with schizophrenia at any time. Adherence is a multidimensional and dynamic concept and it is not useful to consider adherence vs non-adherence as the only categories in the spectrum. Non-adherence is not exclusive to psychosis; it has also been recorded in other psychiatric disorders including depression. In fact, adherence is a problem even in non-psychiatric but long-term illnesses such as diabetes and hypertension. Side-effects are major factors in causing non-adherence. Depot preparations have better adherence rates, largely due to direct supervision and non-reversibility. Lacro JP, et al. Prevalence of and risk factors for medication non adherence in patients with schizophrenia: a comprehensive review of recent literature. Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 2002; 63: 892–909."},{"question":"If a young male is administered 400 mg of lithium once daily, the average time taken for lithium to reach a steady state in plasma is","options":{"A":"1 day","B":"2 days","C":"10 days","D":"4 days","E":"8 days"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The time taken for a drug to reach the steady state is the function of its half-life. If the drug is given regularly within its half-life, it will reach a steady state in the plasma in about four to fi ve half-lives. In this case, Lithium has a half-life of nearly 24 hours. So if we give lithium once daily for 4 days, it would have reached a steady state, and a blood taken on the 4th or 5th morning 12 hours after the last dose will give the trough lithium level, which will be an estimate of the plasma level of lithium. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1279."},{"question":"A 45-year-old man with schizoaffective disorder is on lithium, sertraline, lorazepam, and olanzapine. He develops low sodium levels and complains of extreme lethargy. The most likely offending agent is","options":{"A":"Sertraline","B":"Lithium","C":"Olanzapine","D":"Benzodiazepines","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Hyponatraemia has a well-known association with the use of antidepressants, especially SSRIs. Elderly people and those medically frail are worst affected. Hyponatraemia can also confuse the picture of depression by inducing lethargy and fatigue. The propensity to cause hyponatraemia seems to be a class effect of antidepressants – so replacing an SSRI with another SSRI will not eliminate the risk completely. Carbamazepine is also associated with SIADH and hyponatraemia. Lithium causes nephrogenic diabetes insipidus and sodium levels are either normal or marginally high as a result. Antipsychotics are also reported to be associated with hyponatraemia, although SSRIs are more likely to be associated with this phenomenon. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 159.PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 161"},{"question":"Which of the following predisposes to a nocebo effect?","options":{"A":"The expectation of adverse effects at the start of a treatment","B":"Aversive conditioning","C":"Premorbid neuroticism","D":"Coexistent emotional disturbances","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Placebos can also have adverse effects. Some patients will not tolerate placebos despite the fact that they are inert, and suffer from adverse effects (called the nocebo phenomenon). Nocebo effects with medication include all complaints mistakenly attributed to the medication, such as symptoms of the illness itself, symptoms of stress and the emotional response thereto, symptoms that refl ect the patient’s normal physiology, and symptoms that refl ect normal variations in health. Predisposing factors for a nocebo response include expectations of adverse effects at the onset of treatment, conditioning, wherein the patient learns from prior experiences to associate medication taking with certain somatic symptoms, predisposition due to gender (women complain more), neuroticism, hypochondriasis, a tendency to somatize, coexistent emotional disturbances, and situational and contextual factors that alter expectations or result in aversive conditioning. Barsky AJ, Saintfort R, Rogers MP, and Borus JF. Nonspecifi c medication side effects and the nocebo phenomenon. Journal of the American Medical Association 2002; 287: 622–627."},{"question":"Flumazenil can reverse the effects of an overdose of which of the following drugs?","options":{"A":"Opioids","B":"Ecstasy (MDMA)","C":"Nitrazepam","D":"Valproate","E":"ClozapinePSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS 149"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Flumazenil is an antagonist of benzodiazepine receptors at the GABA complex. It is used A to reverse sedative effects of benzodiazepines used in anaesthesia and in management of benzodiazepine overdose. As a result of this effect, it can precipitate benzodiazepine withdrawal seizures and can also precipitate anxiety in patients with anxiety/ panic disorder. It is not used to treat benzodiazepine withdrawal symptoms. It is not useful for any other drug toxicity or abuse as mentioned in the question. Naloxone is used in opioid overdose. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 317"},{"question":"Regarding depot preparations, which of the following statements is FALSE?","options":{"A":"Depot medications are useful in cases of non-compliance","B":"They undergo less fi rst-pass metabolism than oral preparations","C":"There is less reversibility of side-effects","D":"Injection site reactions are a side-effect","E":"All antipsychotic depot preparations are oil based"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Depot antipsychotic drugs have the following advantages: they decrease the risk of problems associated with medication non-compliance and undergo signifi cantly less fi rst-pass metabolism. The disadvantages include the fact that, once injected, the drug cannot be removed and hence adverse effects or adverse drug interactions are less reversible. An associated complication is injection site reaction. Depot risperidone is an aqueous suspension of risperidone in a glycolic acid–lactate copolymer matrix. The copolymer is slowly hydrolysed, resulting in the gradual release of risperidone. As depot risperidone is water based, it causes fewer reactions than the other oil-based preparations. Grant S and Fitton A. Risperidone: a review of its pharmacology and therapeutic potential in the treatment of schizophrenia. Drugs 1994; 48: 253–273."},{"question":"Which one of the following is NOT a CYP3A4 inducer?","options":{"A":"St. John’s wort","B":"Rifampicin","C":"Barbiturates","D":"Carbamazepine","E":"Fluoxetine"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Fluoxetine is an inhibitor of CYP450 enzymes. CYP1A2 is inhibited by fl uvoxamine and duloxetine, and induced by phenytoin. CYP2D6 is inhibited by fl uoxetine, paroxetine, sertraline, and duloxetine. CYP3A4 is inhibited by fl uoxetine, nefazodone, and sertraline and is induced by carbamazepine, phenobarbital, and phenytoin. CYP2C9/10/19 is inhibited by fl uvoxamine, fl uoxetine, moclobemide, sertraline, and minimally by venlafaxine. St John’s wort induces CYP3A4. CYP3A4 metabolizes carbamazepine, oral contraceptives, atypical antipsychotics, Z hypnotics, benzodiazepines, and calcium channel blockers. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 180"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about fi rst-order kinetics is false?","options":{"A":"A fraction of the drug is eliminated per unit time","B":"Half-life of a drug is directly proportional to the volume of distribution of the drug","C":"Digoxin has a high volume of distribution","D":"Half-life of a drug is directly proportional to the clearance","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"In fi rst order kinetics, a constant fraction of the drug in the body is eliminated per unit time. The rate of elimination is proportional to the amount of drug in the body. The majority of psychiatric drugs are eliminated in this way. Volume of distribution is the amount of drug in the body divided by the concentration in the blood. So a drug that is highly lipid soluble and redistributes into fat has a high volume of distribution (Vd). These drugs stay out of the blood most of the time and, as a result, will have a long half-life. The lesser the clearance of the drug, the longer the half-life; so half-life is inversely proportional to the clearance. Digoxin is highly lipid soluble and has a long half-life. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1287.162 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following is a butyrophenone?","options":{"A":"Risperidone","B":"Quetiapine","C":"Haloperidol","D":"Chlorpromazine","E":"Clozapine"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Risperidone is a benzisoxazole; quetiapine is a dibenzothiazepine; clozapine and is a dibenzodiazepines; olanzapine is a thienobenzodiazepine; sulpiride and amisulpiride are substituted benzamides; chlorpromazine is a phenothazine; and haloperidol is a butyrophenone. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 259."},{"question":"Which of the following medications is NOT associated with zero-order kinetics?","options":{"A":"Phenytoin","B":"Salicylates","C":"Theophylline","D":"Alcohol","E":"Haloperidol"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Zero-order kinetics occurs when the body metabolizes a constant amount of the drug. The metabolic pathway is rapidly saturated, leading to a limit being set for drug elimination. So only a constant amount of drug is eliminated irrespective of plasma levels, for example our body can metabolize around 1 unit of alcohol per hour; if you have taken 4 units, it will take 4 hours for the alcohol to get out of your system. So the time taken is directly proportional to the amount consumed, unlike in fi rst-order kinetics where it takes four to fi ve half-lives for the drug to get out of the system, irrespective of the dose consumed. The most important difference to remember is that a constant fraction (percentage) is eliminated in fi rst-order kinetics while a constant amount is eliminated in zero-order kinetics. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1287."},{"question":"In which of the following situations is a measurement of plasma concentration of a drug the least valuable?","options":{"A":"The drug has a wide therapeutic index","B":"The drug has a therapeutic window","C":"Unexplained toxicity at therapeutic dose","D":"Failure to respond to treatment","E":"Suspected interaction with a co-administered drug150 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Measurement of plasma level is not routinely done for most of the available psychotropic medications. But it is useful, and often indicated, when there is a therapeutic window, suspected drug interactions, unusual toxic reaction at therapeutic doses, and non-response to treatment in spite of administering adequate dose. Therapeutic window is a range of plasma concentration within which a drug produces the therapeutic response. If the level of drug is outside the defi ned ‘window’, the therapeutic response is inadequate. Therapeutic index is a ratio of median toxic dose to median effective dose of a drug. Failure to respond to treatment may be due to non- compliance, which can be detected in some cases by measuring the plasma levels. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 986."},{"question":"The most probable diagnosis in a clozapine-treated patient who has persistent tachycardia, fatigue, fever, and eosinophilia is:","options":{"A":"Pulmonary embolism","B":"Paralytic ileus","C":"Agranulocytosis","D":"Myocarditis","E":"Atypical NMS"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Myocarditis is a fatal complication of clozapine use. It can occur very subtly with observable signs developing well after cardiac failure sets in. This is an idiosyncratic, eosinophilic infl ammation of the myocardium. Persistent tachycardia, fever (fl u like), chest pain, palpitations, dependent oedema, and signs of heart failure must prompt a detailed investigation, including cardiac enzymes (elevated), ECG (ST elevation), ESR (elevated), WBC (eosinophilia), and echocardiogram. With a good monitoring system in place for agranulocytosis, myocarditis is becoming a leading cause of clozapine-related fatalities. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 58."},{"question":"Which of the following patients is at a higher risk of developing lithium- induced hypothyroidism?","options":{"A":"21-year-old man with bipolar disorder","B":"33-year-old man with schizoaffective disorder","C":"45-year-old woman with depression","D":"14-year-old boy with learning diffi culties and aggression","E":"All of the above are at same risk levels"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"It is well established that the risk of hypothyroidism related to lithium use varies widely across the population. Middle-aged women, who probably have a higher risk of having asymptomatic antithyroid antibodies before initiation of lithium, are at the maximum risk of clinical hypothyroidism (up to 20% prevalence). Importantly, this hypothyroidism does not correlate with the dose of lithium prescribed. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 113."},{"question":"Which one of the following regarding mirtazapine is true? It is","options":{"A":"A central alpha 2 autoreceptor antagonist","B":"A serotonin noradrenalin reuptake inhibitor","C":"A selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor","D":"A tricyclic antidepressant","E":"A dopamine noradrenaline reuptake inhibitor"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Mirtazapine is called a noradrenergic and specifi c serotonergic antidepressant (NaSSA). The therapeutic action of mirtazapine is due to central alpha 2 antagonist action, thus cutting the brakes for the release of norepinephrine (alpha 2 inhibitory autoreceptors) and serotonin (alpha 2 heteroreceptors constantly inhibit serotonin release too). Mirtazapine also acts as an antagonist at 5HT , 5HT , and 5HT receptors, which may contribute to the favourable side-effect profi le 2A 2C 3 compared to SSRIs. Mianserin acts in a similar way. Mirtazapine does not block the reuptake pump. Stahl SM. Essential Psychopharmacology: Neuroscientifi c Basis and Practical Application, 2nd edn. Cambridge University Press, 2000, p. 253.PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 163"},{"question":"Which one of the following regarding buspirone is true? It is:","options":{"A":"A tricyclic antidepressant","B":"A selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor","C":"A dopamine antagonist","D":"A partial 5HT agonist","E":"A partial adrenaline agonist"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Buspirone is a partial agonist at 5HT . It is used in generalized anxiety disorder and as an 1A augmenting agent to treat resistant depression. It does not have an action on the GABA receptors; hence it is free from interaction with alcohol and benzodiazepines. It does not lead to dependence or withdrawal symptoms with long-term use. It has a delayed onset of action similar to antidepressants. Stahl SM. Essential Psychopharmacology: Neuroscientifi c Basis and Practical Application, 2nd edn. Cambridge University Press, 2000, p. 273."},{"question":"Which of the following drugs stabilizes dopamine release through its action on dopamine receptors?","options":{"A":"Aripiprazole","B":"Quetiapine","C":"Haloperidol","D":"Olanzapine","E":"Chlorpromazine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Aripiprazole has been dubbed a dopamine system stabilizer due to its partial agonist action. It acts as an agonist where dopamine is depleted and acts as an antagonist where there is an excess of dopamine, making the availability of dopamine ‘just right’ for normal function. Stahl SM. Dopamine system stabilizers, aripiprazole, and the next generation of antipsychotics, part 1, ‘Goldilocks’ actions at dopamine receptors. Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 2001; 62: 841–842."},{"question":"Which one of the following is NOT a cholinesterase inhibitor?","options":{"A":"Rivastigmine","B":"Donepezil","C":"Gallantamine","D":"Organophosphates","E":"MemantinePSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS 151"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Memantine acts by partially blocking NMDA receptors, thereby preventing cell death related to calcium-mediated excitotoxicity. Donepezil is a non-competitive, reversible acetyl cholinesterase inhibitor (AChI). Rivastigmine is a non-competitive inhibitor for both butyryl cholinesterase and acetyl cholinesterase. Gallantamine is a competitive, reversible inhibitor which modulates nicotinic receptors. Tacrine is a non-competitive, non-selective, reversible inhibitor which acts both centrally and peripherally. It is no longer used because of high hepatotoxicity. Organophosphates are often used in pesticides and have acetyl cholinesterase-inhibiting properties. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1033."},{"question":"Which of the following drugs is NOT metabolized by CYP3A4?","options":{"A":"Clozapine","B":"Quetiapine","C":"Ziprasidone","D":"Sertindole","E":"Risperidone"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Among the antipsychotics, typical antipsychotics are mostly metabolized through CYP2D6. Risperidone is metabolized by CYP2D6. Clozapine and olanzapine are primarily metabolized through CYP1A2, and to a lesser extent, through the CYP 3A4 enzyme system. Olanzapine is also metabolized through the CYP3A4 enzyme system. The other antipsychotics listed in Question 24 are metabolized through the CYP3A4 system. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 547."},{"question":"Select one side-effect of antipsychotics that appears earlier than the others when initiating treatment:","options":{"A":"Tardive dyskinesia","B":"Akathisia","C":"Parkinsonism","D":"Hypothyroidism","E":"Weight gain"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Akathisia occurs within hours to days after onset of antipsychotic treatment in most vulnerable cases. Prevalence is thought to be around 25%. It has both a subjective component of inner restlessness and an objective motor restlessness, manifested as constant pacing, shuffl ing, or inability to stand still. A specifi c rating scale to measure akathisia is the Barnes Akathisia Rating Scale. It is to be distinguished from psychotic agitation as akathisia has been linked to suicide and violence. Akathisia can also be caused by serotonergic antidepressants that stimulate 5HT 2 receptors. A slow-developing form of akathisia, called tardive akathisia, may be particularly diffi cult to treat. There is also some evidence to say that persistent akathisia (especially the tardive variant) may predict the development of tardive dyskinesia in the future. Dystonic reactions can occur within minutes of administration of injectable antipsychotics in vulnerable individuals. They are less common with the atypical antipsychotics compared to highly potent, typical antipsychotics (prevalence 10%). Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 76."},{"question":"Which of the following antidementia drugs is/are prescribed for administration once daily?","options":{"A":"Rivastigmine only","B":"Donepezil only","C":"Gallantamine only","D":"Both rivastigmine and donepezil","E":"Both gallantamine and rivastigmine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Donepezil is administered once daily. This is possible because of the extended half-life of donepezil compared to other antidementia drugs. Gallantamine and rivastigmine are administered twice daily. An extended release form of gallantamine is now available and this can be administered once daily. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1035.164 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"The effect of paroxetine on sleep is mainly due to its action on","options":{"A":"5HT 1A","B":"5HT 2A","C":"5HT 3","D":"Histamine receptors","E":"Cholinergic receptors"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Unlike tricyclic antidepressants, most SSRIs have a disruptive effect on sleep, hence administered in the morning. Stimulation of serotonin 5HT receptors in the brainstem sleep 2A centres may cause rapid muscle movements called myoclonus during the night; it may also disrupt slow-wave sleep and cause nocturnal awakenings. 5 HT and 5HT are also responsible for the 2A 2C panic attacks and anxiety associated with SSRIs. 5HT receptors are involved in the gastrointestinal 3 side-effects like nausea and vomiting, mediated through their location at the chemoreceptor trigger zone. SSRIs generally have very much less or absent antihistamine or anticholinergic action, except paroxetine which has signifi cant anticholinergic activity. The antidepressant action of SSRIs is thought to be mediated through the down-regulation of 5HT autoreceptors. 1A Stahl SM. Essential Psychopharmacology: Neuroscientifi c Basis and Practical Application, 2nd edn. Cambridge University Press, 2000, p. 233"},{"question":"Which one of the following is NOT an idiosyncratic reaction?","options":{"A":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome with antipsychotics","B":"Parkinsonism with antipsychotics","C":"Hepatotoxicity with valproate","D":"Stevens Johnson syndrome with carbamazepine","E":"Rash with lamotrigine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Side-effects are generally divided into two types. Dose-dependent side-effects can be predicted, for example postural hypotension or parkinsonian side-effects with antipsychotics. Dose-independent side-effects are either idiosyncratic or immune-mediated side-effects that cannot be predicted in a patient beforehand, for example anaphylactic reactions. Lamotrigine- induced rash is dose independent and often occurs during the early phase of treatment. Hepatotoxicity due to valproate and Steven Johnson syndrome related to carbamazepine are potentially life-threatening, idiosyncratic effects. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1282; Table 3."},{"question":"Which of the following is a dose-dependent side-effect?","options":{"A":"Hepatotoxicity due to naltrexone","B":"Agranulocytosis with clozapine","C":"NMS with antipsychotics","D":"Pancreatitis with valproate","E":"Toxic epidermic necrolysis with lamotrigine152 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Agranulocytosis can occur at any given dose of clozapine. It is not a dose-dependent effect. The risk of agranulocytosis is higher in the fi rst year of clozapine therapy and gradually reduces over the course of treatment. Similarly, neuroleptic malignant syndrome is an idiosyncratic reaction which cannot be predicted in an individual patient. The most important clinical implication to remember is the fact that if a patient has an idiosyncratic side-effect, then this can reoccur at even small doses if rechallenged. Stopping the drug rather than lowering its dose is the appropriate management strategy in such cases. Naltrexone produces hepatocellular damage in proportion to the dose administered, especially in patients with pre-existing liver damage. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 1282; Table 3."},{"question":"Which one of the following affects blood levels of lithium?","options":{"A":"NSAIDS","B":"ACE inhibitors","C":"Thiazide diuretics","D":"Dehydration","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The clearance of lithium is delayed by most non-steroidal anti-infl ammatory drugs including cyclo-oxygenase 2 (COX-2) inhibitors. Thiazide diuretics increase the plasma concentration of lithium. Other drugs which increase the concentration of lithium include ACE inhibitors. SSRIs increase the risk of serotonin syndrome with lithium, while haloperidol and carbamazepine increase the risk of neurotoxicity without altering plasma levels. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 114."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true about plasma levels of clozapine?","options":{"A":"Plasma level monitoring is recommended once weekly for the fi rst 6 months","B":"Plasma levels increase when a smoker stops smoking","C":"In schizophrenia, the recommended plasma level is 150 µg/l","D":"Plasma level is decreased by fl uoxetine","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Clozapine plasma level monitoring is indicated in patients who are not responding to standard doses of clozapine. A plasma level of 350 µg/l is reasonable for most patients. A full blood count is done initially weekly while starting clozapine, in accordance with the clozapine patient monitoring service guidelines. Smoking induces the enzymes that metabolize clozapine. Hence, stopping smoking can increase the levels of clozapine. Fluoxetine is an inhibitor of CYP1A2, which metabolizes clozapine and may increase the levels of clozapine. This may also be therapeutic at times, in patients who do not respond to a maximum dose of clozapine. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 47.PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 165"},{"question":"A ‘therapeutic window’ is well established in which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Imipramine","B":"Lofepramine","C":"Nortriptyline","D":"Sertraline","E":"Citalopram"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"A therapeutic window is a range of concentrations of a drug measured in the blood that are associated with a good therapeutic response. Plasma concentrations outside this range are either too low to ensure a therapeutic response or so high that they induce toxic side-effects. There is no evidence to say that there is an established therapeutic window for neuroleptics. Lithium has a therapeutic window. Nortriptyline is the only medication in the list that appears to have an established therapeutic window, in the range of 50 to 150 ng/ml. This level is usually reached by doses ranging from 50 to 100 mg/day. Leonard BE. Fundamentals of Psychopharmacology, 3rd edn. Wiley, 2003, p. 81."},{"question":"A 30-year-old man is started on amitriptyline. He develops dry mouth, constipation, and blurred vision. Action on which of the following receptors could explain the side-effects described?","options":{"A":"Dopamine","B":"Histamine","C":"Muscarinic","D":"Norepinephrine","E":"Serotonin"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The side-effects mentioned in the question are features suggestive of the action of the tricyclic antidepressant on muscarinic cholinergic receptors. This includes dry mouth, urinary retention, blurred vision, and constipation. Dry mouth may lead to caries teeth in the long term. In the case of overdose with TCA, the anticholinergic action can lead to confusion, coma, and death due to respiratory failure. Action on α-adrenoceptors, may result in postural hypotension, causing falls and injuries. Therapeutic action of TCAs is thought to be due to its inhibitor action on serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake pumps. Amoxapine is a tricyclic antidepressant of the dibenzoxazepine class, which has a dopamine receptor blocking effect. Amoxapine may be useful in cases of psychotic depression due to its dopamine blocking properties. Henry JA. Toxicity of newer versus older antidepressants. Advances in Psychiatric Treatment 1997; 3: 41–45."},{"question":"Which of the following is an example of a pharmacodynamic drug interaction?","options":{"A":"Antacids reduce absorption of chlorpromazine","B":"Valproate displaces warfarin from albumin","C":"Carbamazapine induces the metabolic enzymes","D":"Serotonin syndrome when SSRIs and TCAs are combined","E":"Lithium elimination is decreased by thiazides"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"There are two main types of drug interactions, pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetic. Pharmacodynamic interactions arise when one drug increases or decreases the pharmacological effect of a second drug that is given at the same time, for example the depressant action of alcohol is augmented by benzodiazepines. When one drug alters a pharmacokinetic component of another drug, thus causing a change in the concentration of the other drug, this is called a pharmacokinetic interaction, for example inhibition of CYP450 enzyme, displacement of a drug from protein binding, reduced renal excretion of a drug, etc. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 521."},{"question":"Considering psychopharmacology in perinatal psychiatry, which one of the following is true?","options":{"A":"Absolute risk of Ebstein’s anomaly in patients treated with lithium is 0.05 to 0.1%","B":"Low-potency, typical antipsychotics are preferred to high-potency drugs","C":"Tricyclic antidepressants should be avoided in pregnancy","D":"SSRIs do not cause neonatal withdrawal syndromes","E":"Animal studies have found no effect of psychotropic medication on brain development and behaviour of the fetusPSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS 153"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Most psychotropic medications are best avoided in the fi rst trimester. Caution should also be exercised at the time of delivery and early neonatal period. Most medications, including lithium, are secreted in breast milk and should be used with caution. TCAs and fl uoxetine have the best evidence for safety in pregnancy. Lithium can cause Ebstein’s anomaly (cardiac valvular deformity) and fl oppy baby syndrome in newborns. SSRI withdrawal may be seen in newborns, especially if the mother was on short-acting SSRIs immediately prior to delivery. With respect to antipsychotics, high potency drugs are preferred to low potency ones in pregnancy. Anticonvulsant mood stabilizers have a high risk of neural tube defects. Benzodiazepines have a high risk of cleft lip. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 523."},{"question":"Which one of the following is NOT a factor affecting the pharmacokinetics of drugs in elderly people?","options":{"A":"Fall in gastric pH","B":"Decreased hepatic blood fl ow","C":"Reduced glomerular fi ltration rate","D":"Increased proportion of body fat","E":"Decreased serum albumin"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Gut motility and acid secretion decrease with age. Elderly people have more fat relative to muscle mass, less water, and less body protein than younger adults. This leads to an increase in volume of distribution and longer half-life of administered drugs; 35% of renal function is lost by 65 years of age. Gastric pH increases (not decreases, as indicated in the question) due to loss of acidity. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 486. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 299.166 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"ECT is the fi rst-line treatment for which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Life-threatening depression with refusal of fl uid or food","B":"All cases of catatonia","C":"Treatment-resistant schizophrenia","D":"Psychotic depression","E":"Depression with psychomotor retardation"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"All of the given options may are considered as indications for ECT. But according to the Royal College of Psychiatrists and NICE (UK), ECT as a fi rst-line treatment of choice must be restricted to suicidal patients and those whose illness is life threatening due to refusal of food and fl uids. National Institute for Clinical Excellence. Guidance in the Use of Electroconvulsive Therapy (Technology Appraisal Guidance 59). London: NICE, 2003."},{"question":"ECT has been found to be useful in which of the following conditions?","options":{"A":"Uncontrolled status epilepticus","B":"On–off phenomena in Parkinson’s disease","C":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","D":"Hypopituitarism","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"ECT has been found to be useful in some physical conditions, including those listed in the question, as well as symptoms associated with tardive dystonia. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1120."},{"question":"Which of the following is an absolute contraindication for ECT?","options":{"A":"Pregnancy","B":"Intracranial mass","C":"Presence of a metal skull plate","D":"Presence of implanted pacemaker","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"There are no absolute contraindications for ECT. All the known contraindications are relative. Any medical illness that could compromise the patient’s status under general anaesthesia is considered a relative contraindication. ECT has been reported to be safe in people with pacemakers and metal skull plates, though caution is needed. ECT is safe in pregnancy and is a preferred treatment in depressed, pregnant patients with a high risk to self or the baby. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 1120."},{"question":"Which of the following statements regarding memory problems associated with ECT is true?","options":{"A":"Amnesia is dependent on the dose of electricity.","B":"Amnesia is not related to electrode placement.","C":"Amnesia for personal events is more common than that for public events.","D":"ECT is commonly followed by persistent anterograde amnesia.","E":"None of the above."},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Amnesia is dependent on the dose of electricity that exceeds the threshold stimulus needed to elicit a seizure in a given patient. The higher the dose, the greater the memory disturbance. It is also dependent on the electrode placement and more severe with bilateral placement than unilateral. Remote memory loss for impersonal/ public events is more common than amnesia for personal events. ECT is rarely followed by persistent anterograde amnesia. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 568."},{"question":"The most common cause for mortality in ECT is","options":{"A":"Fracture of the dorsal vertebrae","B":"Cardiac arrhythmia","C":"Status epilepticus","D":"Herniation of the brain","E":"Electrical burns caused due to poor contact of electrodes154 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Mortality with ECT is about the same as that with general anaesthesia for any minor surgery. The American Psychiatric Association Task Force on ECT estimated that the ECT-related mortality rate is 1 in 10,000 patients or 1 in 80,000 treatments. ECT is considered a low-risk procedure, even in an elderly cardiac patient who, in the developed world, is fast becoming the modal candidate for ECT. It is noted that ECT is about 10 times safer than childbirth and, each year, approximately six times as many deaths in the USA are caused by lightning than by ECT. In those who die, the commonest cause is a cardiac event, usually an arrhythmia. Abrams R. The mortality rate with ECT. Convulsive Therapy 1997; 13: 125–127."},{"question":"When comparing unilateral and bilateral ECT which of the following is true?","options":{"A":"Memory defi cits are less common with bilateral than unilateral ECT","B":"Unilateral ECT is most effective at 2.5 times the seizure threshold","C":"Unilateral ECT is more effective compared to bilateral","D":"Bilateral ECT acts faster than unilateral ECT","E":"Unilateral ECT has better synergistic properties with antidepressants"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Overall, bilateral ECT has superior effi cacy compared to unilateral, although bilateral is associated with more side-effects. Recent studies have shown that high-dose unilateral is better than low-dose bilateral in terms of side-effects and equivalent in terms of effi cacy. When choosing right unilateral placement, a higher dose titration is preferred. If there is a need for urgent improvement, bilateral placement is recommended. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 567."},{"question":"Which of the following has the shortest plasma half-life?","options":{"A":"Zolpidem","B":"Zaleplon","C":"Zopiclone","D":"Temazepam","E":"Clomethiazole"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Z hypnotics are non-benzodiazepines which act at or close to the benzodiazepine receptor site in the GABA complex. Its action is reversed by fl umazenil. Zaleplon has the A shortest half-life (1 hour) among the sedatives listed in the question. Temazepam (5–11 hours) and clomethiazole (4–6 hours) are also used as hypnotics. They are usually prescribed short term for the induction of sleep, usually for not more than 2 weeks. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 529.PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 167"},{"question":"An elderly gentleman recently started on a hypnotic complains of sneezing and conjunctival irritation. He was most probably started on which of the following drugs?","options":{"A":"Temazepam","B":"Melatonin","C":"Zopiclone","D":"Clomethiazole","E":"Zaleplon"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Clomethiazole is a hypnotic with anticonvulsant properties. It causes dependence and respiratory depression with alcohol. It is used in elderly people because of its relatively shorter half-life. Unwanted side-effects include sneezing, conjunctival irritation, and nausea. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 530."},{"question":"Which of the following is the most potent depot antipsychotic in terms of mg per mg?","options":{"A":"Risperidone long acting","B":"Haloperidol decanoate","C":"Fluphenazine decanoate","D":"Flupentixol decanoate","E":"Pipotiazine palmitate"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Pipothiazine is the most potent in terms of dose–response of the depot neuroleptics; 5 mg of pipothiazine is equivalent to: 100 mg of haloperidol, 25 mg of risperidone, 25 mg of fl uphenazine, 40 mg of fl upentixol, and 200 mg of zuclopenthixol. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 533."},{"question":"Which of the following antipsychotics is a drug of choice for a patient with hepatic impairment?","options":{"A":"Risperidone","B":"Amisulpride","C":"Olanzapine","D":"Quetiapine","E":"Aripiprazole"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Most antipsychotics, with the notable exception of amisulpiride, are highly lipid soluble and extensively metabolized by the liver. Amisulpiride is excreted unchanged by the kidney. Amisulpride is also considered unique in that it is a highly selective dopamine D2/D3 receptor antagonist that binds preferentially to receptors in the mesolimbic system. It is also an ‘atypical’ antipsychotic despite, having a different receptor-affi nity profi le compared to the other atypical antipsychotics (i.e. absence of serotonin antagonism). At low doses (50 mg), amisulpride preferentially blocks presynaptic autoreceptors, producing an increase in dopamine release, leading to some amelioration of the dopaminergic hypoactivity seen in negative symptoms of schizophrenia and depression. At higher doses (400–1200 mg), the drug exerts its activity on postsynaptic D/D receptors located in the limbic region and prefrontal areas, producing 3 2 selective dopaminergic inhibition. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 533."},{"question":"Which of the following antipsychotics has the LEAST effect on weight gain?","options":{"A":"Aripiprazole","B":"Olanzapine","C":"Quetiapine","D":"Risperidone","E":"Clozapine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Clozapine and olanzapine produce the maximum weight gain among antipsychotics. Aripiprazole is considered to be weight neutral, according to the currently available data. Ziprasidone, which is not marketed in the UK, is said to be associated with some weight loss. Average increases reported during the fi rst year are 5.3 to 6.3 kg for clozapine and 6.8 to 11.8 kg for olanzapine, with some subgroups gaining more than 20% of their initial body weight. Moreover, Leiberman et al., found that weight gain appears to be a continuous process where no relationship exists between the dose of antipsychotics prescribed and degree of weight gain. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 532. Lieberman JA, Stroup TS, McEvoy JP, et al. Effectiveness of antipsychotic drugs in patients with chronic schizophrenia. New England Journal of Medicine 2005; 353: 1209–1223."},{"question":"Which of the following is a dibenzothiazepine in its chemical structure?","options":{"A":"Risperidone","B":"Clozapine","C":"Olanzapine","D":"Quetiapine","E":"Amisulpride"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Quetiapine is a dibenzothiazepine. It acts similar to clozapine; both drugs having a ‘hit- and-run’ profi le on D receptors. Quetiapine does not stay at the receptor site for a long time to 2 produce extrapyramidal effects but instead it produces a transient blockade. This has been demonstrated using 11C Raclopride PET studies. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 531. Kapur S, Zipursky RB et al. A positron emission tomography study of quetiapine in schizophrenia: a preliminary fi nding of an antipsychotic effect with only transiently high dopamine D2 receptor occupancy. Archives of General Psychiatry 2000; 57: 553–559.168 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following is true about tardive dyskinesia?","options":{"A":"Develops in up to 50% of patients treated with schizophrenia","B":"Risk factor include being a young male with a history of mood disorder","C":"TD is said to be due to the down regulation of dopamine receptors","D":"Stopping the antipsychotics worsens TD temporarily","E":"Anticholinergics such as procyclidine are the treatment of choice"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"In tardive dyskinesia (TD) the movements can be choreiform, athetoid, dystonic, stereotypic, or a combination of these. They most commonly involve the orobuccal, lingual, and facial muscles. High risk groups includes women, elderly, patients with underlying brain damage, those with mood disorder or schizoaffective illness, learning disability, and, curiously, patients with diabetes. It is seen in up to 20% of people on long-term antipsychotic medications. The pathophysiology behind TD is considered to be receptor up-regulation (increase in postsynaptic receptor numbers due to chronic pharmacological antagonism). So, increasing the dose of the offending drugs may suppress the dyskinetic movements for a short while. Anticholinergic drugs, on the other hand, may aggravate TD. Strategies for the management of tardive dyskinesia include gradual withdrawal of antipsychotic medication, a switch to clozapine, and discontinuation of the anticholinergic medication. Tetrabenazine has been considered to be effective as it depletes dopamine from nerve endings. This makes super-sensitivity reactions less likely in spite of an increase in receptor numbers. But the risk of depression is very high with tetrabenazine (similar to reserpine). Clonazepam, diazepam, vitamin E, and melatonin are other proposed management options. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 78."},{"question":"Which of the following drugs has the greatest effect on QTc interval?","options":{"A":"Quetiapine","B":"Thioridazine","C":"Olanzapine","D":"Aripiprazole","E":"Risperidone"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Pimozide and thioridazine have been found to increase the QT interval. The QT interval (from the Q wave to the end of the T wave) varies with the heart rate, gender, and time of day. There are several different ways of correcting QT for heart rate (QTc), but the simplest method is using Bazett’s formula. In this method, the corrected QT interval (QTc) is calculated by the equation QTc = QT/(cid:1)RR. It is, however, uncertain whether QT has any greater clinical C signifi cance than the uncorrected QT interval. The normal QT interval is 340–430 ms, and irrespective of the heart rate, a QT interval >450 ms is probably risky. A prolonged QT interval can predispose to polymorphic ventricular arrhythmias (torsades de pointes). Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 87."},{"question":"Which of the following is potentially antagonistic at dopamine receptors?","options":{"A":"Imipramine","B":"Clomipramine","C":"Amoxapine","D":"Amitriptyline","E":"Nortriptyline"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Amoxapine is a TCA with fairly selective inhibition of noradrenaline reuptake. It also has D2 antagonist property. This pharmacological profi le suggests a good option for the treatment of psychotic depression. But in addition to the side-effects of TCA, there is also an additional risk of side-effects associated with D2 antagonism. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 542."},{"question":"Which of the following tricyclic antidepressants is the preferred drug compared to the others listed when prescribed to a patient with cardiovascular illness?","options":{"A":"Imipramine","B":"Clomipramine","C":"Lofepramine","D":"Amitriptyline","E":"Nortriptyline"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Cardiovascular side-effects of tricyclics include hypotension and tachycardia. Conduction abnormalities, ECG changes, ventricular arrhythmias, and heart blocks are complications seen especially in people with pre-existing heart disease. Lofepramine is a tertiary amine which is metabolized to desipramine, a secondary amine. Inspite of being a tertiary amine, lofepramine is more selective for norepinephrine reuptake inhibition. It has a better side-effect profi le compared to other TCAs. It is also less cardiotoxic than other TCAs. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 543."},{"question":"Which of the following is more common with SSRIs compared to TCAs?","options":{"A":"Switch to mania","B":"Seizures","C":"Parkinsonian side-effects","D":"Cardiac side-effects","E":"None of the above156 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"SSRIs are safer than TCAs as far as cardiotoxicity, switch to mania, and seizures are concerned. But SSRIs are more prone to cause extrapyramidal reaction, possibly due to an increase in serotonin at 5HT heteroceptors on dopaminergic neurones. Some of the SSRIs may also have a low degree of intrinsic antagonistic action at the dopaminergic receptors. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 546.PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS 169"},{"question":"Serotonin syndrome is possible when SSRIs are combined with which of the following?","options":{"A":"Lithium","B":"MAOIs","C":"Sumatriptan","D":"Tryptophan","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Serotonin syndrome is a potentially fatal syndrome occurring in the context of initiation or dose increase of a serotonergic agent. This syndrome is characterized by altered mental state, agitation, tremor, shivering, diarrhoea, hyper-refl exia, myoclonus, ataxia, and hyperthermia. It could also occur during combination antidepressant therapy. These include medications that exert their primary action through the serotonin receptor (SSRI, SNRI, buspirone, etc), MAOIs, and serotonin precursor tryptophan. Serotonin toxicity is also reported to occur when SSRIs are combined with medications whose mode of action is not known (lithium) or medications which may inhibit CYP enzymes and increase SSRI levels in plasma. Sternbach’s criteria are used to diagnose serotonin syndrome. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 870."},{"question":"In a patient with depression, an SSRI would be the drug of choice, EXCEPT when","options":{"A":"The patient has concomitant cardiac disease","B":"Sedation is desired","C":"There is a risk of overdose","D":"History of intolerance to anticholinergic side-effects","E":"Depression is associated with obsessive compulsive symptoms"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"SSRIs are generally not sedating. Sometimes they can be activating, producing initial insomnia, anxiety, or panic attacks. They are relatively safer in overdose compared to TCAs. Apart from paroxetine and to some extent fl uoxetine, most SSRIs have almost absent anticholinergic activity. SSRIs have been found to be more useful in obsessions than the other antidepressant groups. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 358."},{"question":"Which of the following statements regarding drug interactions is true?","options":{"A":"Salbutamol inhalers are safe in patients taking MAOIs.","B":"Combining MAOIs and tricyclics could lead to severe postural hypotension.","C":"MAOIs are sedating at therapeutic doses.","D":"Moclobemide is not associated with tyramine reaction.","E":"Incidence of hypertensive reaction in patients on MAOIs is less than 1%."},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Incidence of hypertensive reaction is about 10% in patients who take MAOIs. Tyramine is a substance usually metabolized by MAO A in the intestinal mucosa. In patients who are taking MAOIs, the breakdown of tyramine is not adequate, leading to the ‘cheese reaction’. Salbutamol, being an agonist at the adrenergic receptor, could precipitate a hypertensive crisis in patients taking MAOIs. The combination of TCAs and MAOIs could potentially induce severe postural hypotension. Side-effects of MAOIs include anticholinergic side-effects and insomnia, rather than sedation. Phenelzine, tranylcypromine, and isocarboxazid are irreversible inhibitors and non- selectively bind to both MAO A and MAO B. Moclobemide is a selective and reversible MAOI. Although the incidence is less, tyramine reaction can occur even with moclobemide. Gelder MG et al., eds. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry, 5th edn. Oxford University Press, 2006, p. 551."},{"question":"Which of the following is associated with leucocytosis?","options":{"A":"Clozapine","B":"Mianserin","C":"Mirtazapine","D":"Lithium","E":"Carbamazepine"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Lithium is associated with leucocytosis and could be used therapeutically for carbamazepine- or clozapine-induced leucopenia. All the other drugs in the question are associated with leucopenia and agranulocytosis as a result of idiosyncratic drug reaction. Taylor et al., eds. The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines, 8th edn. Taylor and Francis, 2005, p. 60."},{"question":"Which of the following is true with regard to lamotrigine?","options":{"A":"Valproate decreases levels of lamotrigine","B":"Carbamazepine increases the level of lamotrigine","C":"Lamotrigine monotherapy has been found to be effective in bipolar mania","D":"Lamotrigine induces cytochrome enzymes","E":"Lamotrigine blocks voltage-dependent sodium channels"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Lamotrigine acts by blocking voltage-gated sodium channels associated with glutamate receptors. Carbamazepine is an enzyme inducer and decreases lamotrigine levels. Valproate is an enzyme inhibitor and increases lamotrigine levels. So combining lamotrigine with carbamazepine or valproate requires caution. Lamotrigine has been found to be effective as a monotherapy for bipolar depression. It has not been found to be effective in acute mania or relapse prevention of mania in bipolar disorder. Lamotrigine does not induce CYP450 enzymes. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 320.170 PSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following is associated with inappropriate secretion of antidiuretic hormone (SIADH)?","options":{"A":"Fluoxetine","B":"Venlafaxine","C":"Haloperidol","D":"Amitriptyline","E":"All of the abovePSYCHOPHARMACOLOGY | QUESTIONS 157"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"SIADH is an idiosyncratic reaction in response to treatment with antidepressants, especially SSRIs. Old age, diabetes, hypertension, impaired renal function, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) are risk factors for SIADH. SIADH usually presents as unexplained weakness and lethargy. In severe forms it can cause confusion and delirium. Serum Na+ <125 mmol/l and a 24-h urine Na+ >20 mmol/l or osmolality >100 mosml/kg are diagnostic indicators for SIADH. Withdrawal of the offending agent is the most effective intervention, apart from maintaining fl uid balance. It is important to rule out other primary causes of SIADH before concluding it to be a drug-induced effect. It is known to occur with almost all classes of antidepressants. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 874."},{"question":"Which of the following is LESS likely to cause a discontinuation reaction than others in the list?","options":{"A":"Venlafaxine","B":"Fluoxetine","C":"Paroxetine","D":"Citalopram","E":"Amitriptyline"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Fluoxetine has a half-life of up to 72 hours. It also has an active metabolite with similar action, which prolongs the total duration of action up to 2 weeks (norfl uoxetine). So, discontinuation reaction is less likely with fl uoxetine. Paroxetine and citalopram have a half-life of 20 to 30 hours. Discontinuation reaction usually develops after at least a month of SSRI treatment and within 2–5 days after SSRI discontinuation or dose reduction. In general, gradual taper and stopping of the medications are indicated when SSRIs are used. Reinstatement of the same or a longer-acting SSRI can alleviate the symptoms, apart from using benzodiazepines. All classes of antidepressants are known to be associated with discontinuation reactions, including venlafaxine and amitriptyline. Semple DM et al., eds. Oxford Handbook of Psychiatry, 1st edn. Oxford University Press, 2005, p. 872."}]');export{e as default};
